what do you do for a living basically
means what is your job or what do you do
to make money however in conversation we
wouldn't usually ask someone what do you
do to make money or what is your job we
usually ask what do you do for a living
what do you do for work or just what do
you do I'm teacher Mike and today we're
learning how to talk about what you do
for work when introducing yourself in
English so the most common thing that we
say is probably just I'm followed by
your profession for example I'm an
English teacher and content
creator another one that's very similar
is I work
as this one is often used when the job
is temporary or
less connected to your identity it can
sound more like this job is not an
important part of who I am it's just
something that I'm doing right now to
make money for example he's a teacher
but he also works as a cashier on the
weekends another very common way to
explain what you do is to just explain
what you do I verb
for example I create social media
content to help adults who are learning
English as a second language if you want
people to understand exactly what you do
this one is usually the best option
because it tells them what you do you
can also use I work for I work at and I
work in I work for is usually followed
by a type of company or the name of a
company for example I work for a
software company or she works for
Microsoft you could also use this with a
specific person for example he works for
his uncle I work at is usually followed
by a location for example I work at a
bank we can also use it with a company
but when we use work at a company it's a
bit different from work for a company
for example I used to work at batuman
Princess Hotel in Bangkok Thailand the
hotel only has one location and every
day when I went to work I was at that
location so when people asked me where I
worked I usually said I work at batuman
Princess Hotel however there were also
people who worked for the hotel but were
not usually at the hotel for example the
hotel's airport limousine drivers they
worked for the hotel but they spent most
of their time at the airport not at the
hotel and here's another example that
shows the difference for about 1 year I
worked at a TV station two days per week
I would go to their headquarters and
teach a group of
employees however I did not work for
that TV station I worked for a training
center that had a contract with them so
although I worked at the TV station I
did not work for the TV station I work
in is usually followed by a field
department or industry for example she
works in finance or he works in human
resources
and when giving more specific
information about what we really do at
our job we often use I'm responsible for
I'm responsible for basically means that
something is a very important part of
your job and you are the main person who
does this thing for example when I was
the education manager of a Language
Center back in
2017 I was responsible for are hiring
and training new teachers and if you
work for yourself you can say that you
are
self-employed for example I am a
self-employed English teacher and
content creator if you have your own
business you can say that you have your
own business own your own business or
run your own business and you're usually
going to specify what type of business
it is
for example her mother runs a noodle
stand at the night market or my uncle
owns a Japanese
restaurant and if you don't have a job
right now you can say that you are
between jobs or
unemployed unemployed just means that
you don't have a job however it can
sometimes sound a tiny bit negative like
maybe you can't find a job or don't want
a job between jobs means basically the
same thing but it also says that you had
a job before and you're confident that
you will have another job again soon so
between jobs just sounds a bit more
positive whereas unemployed can
sometimes sound a bit negative so what
do you do for a living leave a comment
and let me know